

email 8 Google Scholar Github



in LinkedIn

Professional Summary ____

I am an experienced researcher working at the intersection of machine learning and quantum computing. As the lead of Q-CTRL's Applications and Algorithms team, I design and experimentally implement quantum algorithms, while also leveraging machine learning to improve the performance of near-term quantum computers. I have contributed to high-impact initiatives across academia, public policy, and industry, with a focus on improving the performance of quantum computers, AI/ML applications in defense, computational modeling, and red-teaming large language models. I have a strong track record of leading research teams and bridging the gap between theoretical research and software development, ensuring practical, real-world impact.

Professional Experience ______

Q-CTRL Santa Monica, CA

LEAD SCIENTIST June 2022 - present

- · Team lead for the Applications and Algorithms Team, driving experimental demonstrations of quantum algorithms
- Improved large-scale entangled state generation with quantum error correction primitives
- Designed and implemented a machine learning approach for quantum circuit layout selection
- Developed a state-of-the-art and GPU-accelerated photonic circuit simulation and optimization engine
- Established a robust quantum optimization pipeline

The RAND Corporation

Santa Monica, CA

INFORMATION SCIENTIST

Aug. 2017 - May 2022

- Served as AI/ML Lead for the Tech and Narrative Lab, guiding research in AI/ML applications
- Launched and organized a company-wide AI seminar series, fostering cross-disciplinary collaboration
- Co-PI for a **generative modeling for social networks** project, leading to novel applications
- Researched adversarial vulnerabilities in autonomous systems, influencing defense against cyber threats
- Improved object detection models using synthetic datasets, enhancing real-world applicability
- Modeled COVID-19 across city-scale contact networks, providing insights for public health interventions

Large Language Model Red-Teaming

Santa Monica, CA

Sept. 2022 - Oct. 2023

INDEPENDENT CONSULTING

- Worked with Meta to red-team their language models
- Worked with OpenAI to red-team GPT-4

University of Southampton

Southampton, United Kingdom

Sept. 2015 - Aug. 2017

- POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCH FELLOW
- Studied theoretical properties of black holes and quantum field theories
- Worked on multiple projects as part of an international collaboration
- Co-organized 3 seminar series
- Traveled extensively to present research and facilitate collaborations

Education_

University of California, Santa Barbara

Santa Barbara, CA

Aug. 2009 - May 2015

PHD and MA in Physics

• Adviser: Prof. Garv Horowitz

• Dissertation: Aspects of Black Holes in Higher Dimensions

Syracuse University

Syracuse, NY

Sept. 2005 - May 2009

BSC IN PHYSICS AND MATHEMATICS

- Summa Cum Laude
- Honors Thesis: Spiral Patterns in Liquid Crystals

Technical Publications

Achieving computational gains with quantum error correction primitives: Generation of long-range entanglement enhanced by error detection

H. Liao, G. S. Hartnett, A. Kakkar, A. Tan, M. Hush, P. S. Mundada, M. J. Biercuk, Y. Baum. arXiv:2411.14638 [quant.ph]
Preprint

Resource-efficient context-aware dynamical decoupling embedding for arbitrary large-scale quantum algorithms

P. Coote, R. Dimov, S. Maity, G. S. Hartnett, M. J. Biercuk, Y. Baum. arXiv:2409.05962 [quant.ph]
Preprint

Quantum optimization using a 127-qubit gate-model IBM quantum computer can outperform quantum annealers for nontrivial binary optimization problems

N. Sachdeva, G. S. Hartnett, S. Maity, S. Marsh, Y. Wang, A. Winick, R. Dougherty, D. Canuto, Y. Q. Chong, M. Hush, P. S. Mundada, C. D. B. Bentley, M. J. Biercuk, Y. Baum. arXiv:2406.01743 [quant.ph]
Preprint

· Learning to rank quantum circuits for hardware-optimized performance enhancement

G. S. Hartnett, A. Barbosa, P. S. Mundada, M. Hush, M. J. Biercuk, Y. Baum. arXiv:2404.06535 [quant.ph] Quantum 8, 1542 (2024)

Twisty-puzzle-inspired approach to Clifford synthesis

N. Bao, G. S. Hartnett. arXiv:2307.08684 [quant.ph] Phys. Rev. A 109, issue 3, 032409 (2024)

• The Karzas-Latter-Seiler Model of a High-Altitude Electromagnetic Pulse: A New Numerical Code for an Old Model

G. S. Hartnett. arXiv:2402.14864 [physics.plasm-ph] RAND Working Paper WRA879-2

· The hierarchical parity model

G. S. Hartnett. arXiv:2208.13316 [cond-mat.dis-nn] Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications 617 (2023): 128679.

 Modeling the Impact of Social Distancing and Targeted Vaccination on the Spread of COVID-19 through a Real City-Scale Contact Network

G. Ś. Hartnett, E. Parker, T. R. Gulden, R. Vardavas, D. Kravitz. arXiv:2107.06213 [physics.soc-ph] Journal of Complex Networks 9.6 (2021): cnab042.

· Protecting the Most Vulnerable by Vaccinating the Most Active

T. R. Gulden, G. S. Hartnett, R. Vardavas, D. Kravitz. RAND Perspective PE-A1068-1

· Deep Generative Modeling in Network Science with Applications to Public Policy Research

G. S. Hartnett, R. Vardavas, L. Baker, M. Chaykowsky, C. B. Gibson, F. Girosi, D. P. Kenedy, O. A. Osoba. arXiv:2010.07870 [cs.LG]
RAND Working Paper WRA843-1

Self-Supervised Learning of Generative Spin-Glasses with Normalizing Flows

G. S. Hartnett, M. Mohseni. arXiv:2001.00585 [cs.LG] Preprint

· A Probability Density Theory for Spin-Glass Systems

G. S. Hartnett, M. Mohseni. arXiv:2001.00927 [cond-mat.dis-nn] Preprint Operationally Relevant Artificial Training for Machine Learning: Improving the Performance of Automated Target Recognition Systems

G. S. Hartnett, L. Menthe, J. Léveillé, D. Baveye, L. Zhang, D. Gold, J. Hagen, J. Xu. RAND Report RRA683-1 (2020)

· Covariant Noether charges for type IIB and 11-dimensional supergravities

O. J. C. Dias, G. S. Hartnett, J. E. Santos. arXiv:1912.01030 [hep-th] Class. Quant. Grav. 31, no. 1, 015003 (2021)

Adversarial Examples for Cost-Sensitive Classifiers

G. S. Hartnett, A. J. Lohn, A. P. Sedlack. arXiv:1910.02095 [stat-ML] Workshop on Safety and Robustness in Decision Making, NeurIPS 2019

Holographic dual of hot Polchinski-Strassler quark-gluon plasma
 Description of the Polchinski-Strassler quark-gluon plasma

I. Bena, O. J. C. Dias, G. S. Hartnett, Benjamin. E. Niehoff, J. E. Santos. arXiv:1805.06463 [hep-th] JHEP 9, 33 2019

Replica Symmetry Breaking in Bipartite Spin Glasses and Neural Networks

G. S. Hartnett, E. Parker, E. Geist. arXiv:1803.06442 [cond-mat.dis-nn; cs.LG] Phys. Rev. E 98, issue 2, 022116 (2018)

· Constraining the mass of dark photons and axion-like particles through black-hole superradiance

V. Cardoso, Ö. J. C. Dias, G. S. Hartnett, M. Middleton, P. Pani, J. E. Santos. arXiv:1801.01420 [gr-qc] JCAP 1803, no.03, 043 (2018)

Mass-deformed M2 branes in Stenzel space

O. J. C. Dias, G. S. Hartnett, B. E. Niehoff, J. E. Santos. arXiv:1704.02323 [hep-th] JHEP 1711, 105 (2017)

· Localised Anti-Branes in Flux Backgrounds

G. S. Hartnett. arXiv:1501.06568 [hep-th] JHEP 1506, 007 (2015)

· A No Black Hole Theorem

G. S. Hartnett, G. T. Horowitz and K. Maeda. arXiv:1410.1875 [hep-th] Class. Quant. Grav. 32, no. 5, 055011 (2015)

Quasinormal modes of asymptotically flat rotating black holes

O. J. C. Dias, G. S. Hartnett and J. E. Santos. arXiv:1402.7047 [hep-th] Class. Quant. Grav. 31, no. 24, 245011 (2014)

Holographic thermalization, quasinormal modes and superradiance in Kerr-AdS

V. Cardoso, O. J. C. Dias, G. S. Hartnett, L. Lehner and J. E. Santos. arXiv:1312.5323 [hep-th] JHEP 1404, 183 (2014)

· Non-Axisymmetric Instability of Rotating Black Holes in Higher Dimensions

G. S. Hartnett and J. E. Santos. arXiv:1306.4318 [gr-qc] Phys. Rev. D 88, 041505 (2013)

· Geons and Spin-2 Condensates in the AdS Soliton

G. S. Hartnett and G. T. Horowitz. arXiv:1210.1606 [hep-th] JHEP 1301, 010 (2013)

Policy Publications

 Understanding the Limits of Artificial Intelligence for Warfighters: Volume 2: Distributional Shift in Cybersecurity Datasets

J. J. Steier, E. Van Hegewald, A. Jacques, G. S. Hartnett, L. Menthe. RAND Report RR-A1722-2 (2024)

- Cybersecurity and Supply Chain Risk Management Are Not Simply Additive V. A. Greenfield, J. W. Welburn, K. Schwindt, D. Ish, A. J. Lohn, G. S. Hartnett. RAND Report RR-A532-1 (2023)
- Operational Feasibility of Adversarial Attacks Against Artificial Intelligence
 L. A. Zhang, G. S. Hartnett, J. Aguirre, A. J. Lohn, I. Khan, M. Herron, and C. O'Connell.
 RAND Report RR-A866-1 (2022)
- Empirical Evaluation of Physical Adversarial Patch Attacks Against Overhead Object Detection Models
 G. S Hartnett, L. Zhang, C. O'Connell, A. J. Lohn, J. Aguirre.
 arXiv:2206.12725
- Airline Security Through Artificial Intelligence
 S. McKay, G. S. Hartnett, B. Held.
 RAND Report PEA731-1
- Maintaining the Competitive Advantage in Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning
 R. Waltzman, L. Ablon, C. Curriden, G. Hartnett, M. Holliday, L. Ma, B. Nichiporuk, A. Scobell, D. Tarraf.
 RAND Report RRA200

Teaching

Pardee RAND Graduate School

Santa Monica, CA

2018-2022

CORE FACULTY MEMBER/PROFESSOR

ember/Professor

- · Introduction to Modern AI
- Introduction to Blockchain Technology

University of Southampton

Southampton, UK

LECTURER Sept. 2015 - May 2015

- MATH1052 Differential Equations
- MATH1008 Mathematical Methods
- MATH3071 Light and Waves

University of California, Santa Barbara

Santa Barbara, CA

HEAD TEACHING ASSISTANT

Aug. 2010 - Aug. 2012

Sept. 2009 - May 2015

- Managed team of 40+ TA's for the entire Physics Department
- Worked with faculty and staff to assign TA's to courses

TEACHING ASSISTANT

- PHYS6L Introductory Physics (3 quarters)
- PHYS21 General Physics
- PHYS105 Classical Mechanics
- PHYS115 Quantum Mechanics (2 quarters)
- PHYS219 Statistical Mechanics (graduate level)

Professional Activities_____

FOUNDER AND ORGANIZER OF AI SEMINAR SERIES AT THE RAND CORPORATION ORGANIZER OF GRADUATE STUDENT HIGH-ENERGY JOURNAL CLUB

2018 - 2022

2012 - 2014

REFEREE FOR

- Ethics Reviewer for NeurIPS 2021
- ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (FAccT) 2020
- NeurIPS 2019 Workshop: Machine Learning and the Physical Sciences
- Journal of High Energy Physics (JHEP)
- · Physical Letters B

- Classical and Quantum Gravity
- General Relativity and Gravitation

Awards_____

2021	RAND Spotlight Award , awarded for a study assessing how AI could be used to improve	Santa Monica, CA
	the TSA baggage screening process	
	RAND Bronze Medal Award , company-wide annual award, awarded for "vision, integrity,	
2020	and leadership" in the course of a project on adversarial machine learning for cyber	Santa Monica, CA
	defense systems.	
2019	RAND Spotlight Award , awarded for "developing a new game theoretic approach with	Santa Monica, CA
	Machine Learning techniques to assess cyber defense capabilities."	
	RAND Project Air Force Team Innovation Award, awarded for our team's	
2019	$\hbox{``high-risk/high-reward approach to solving a complex technical problem-understanding'}$	Santa Monica, CA
	how machine learning-based algorithms might be vulnerable to cyber attack"	
2014	Dean's Fellowship, Competitive University-wide fellowship	Santa Barbara, CA
2013	James Hartle Award, Best graduate student talk	Warsaw, Poland
2011	Chairs Certificate of Appreciation, Outstanding service as Head TA	Santa Barbara, CA
2009	Syracuse University Scholar, Highest undergraduate academic honor	Syracuse, NY
2008	Barry Goldwater Scholarship, Most prestigious undergraduate national science award	Syracuse, NY